<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4444/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4444/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-09-28T00:39:08-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4444/blog/</id><title type="html">Iris Liu</title><subtitle>A blog of a computer scientist and ultra runner</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Goodbye 2019</title><link href="http://localhost:4444/blog/bucket-list-2019" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Goodbye 2019" /><published>2020-01-01T02:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-01-01T02:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4444/blog/bucket-list-2019</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4444/blog/bucket-list-2019">&lt;p&gt;I was leaving for Los Angelos on 24th December 2019. At the time, I created this bucket list to create memories with families and friends before leaving Home Kong 🇭🇰! Goodbye for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Christmas Hotpot - ✅ Dec 14th (What’s better than a dinner gathering with friends in a round table with hotpot and christmas gifts?!)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Veggie Dim Sum&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Taste best egglets in HK - ✅ (Egglets used to be my childhood favorite)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Veggie Buffet in SZ - ✅ Nov 7th (The veggie buffet is recommended by a meditation friend, the spot is low-key, yet one of the best quality)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/HaidilaoHK/&quot;&gt;Haidilao Hot Pot 海底撈&lt;/a&gt;🌶🌶 - ✅ Dec 1st (Went for the satisfying hotpot after the twin peaks hike with my girls)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hike/ run the TWINS - ✅ Dec 1st&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lantau 2 Peaks - ✅ December (Went with my running crew. I slept over that morning OOPS, and )&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;High Junk Peak&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hike Wu Tong Mountain in SZ - ✅ Nov 7th 2019&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Beach Clean up - Tigerhead plogging - ✅ Aug 24th 2019 (Beach cleanup and jogging)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wake Surf&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HK50 race - ✅ Oct 26th (Race of the year 2019)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Camp on Lantau island- ✅ Nov 16th&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run entire HK trail (~45Km) - ✅ Oct 12th (To celebrate Amanda’s birthday, we run the entire HK trail 45Km)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Watch Swan Lake ballet show at Cultural Center - ✅ Nov 12th 2019&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visit Tai Kwun Centre for Heritage and Art - ✅ (Went with Karen after our lebanese dinner)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take a BJJ class - ✅ Dec 11th 2019 (Jocelyn showed me her go-to BJJ spot)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Serve for a 3-day &lt;a href=&quot;https://mutta.dhamma.org/&quot;&gt;Vipassana Meditation&lt;/a&gt; camp - ✅ Aug 2019 (One of the best life experience I’ve ever had - it’s a lifelong practise!)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Volunteer for local service at &lt;a href=&quot;http://nowandzenn.blogspot.com/2011/09/volunteering-at-home-of-loves-soup.html&quot;&gt;Missionaries of charity&lt;/a&gt; in SSP - ✅ Nov 31rd&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Donate my clothings / stuff to people in need&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Join a live music show - ✅ (my friend has an amzing vocal)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learn social latin dance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Win a hackathon - Zoohackathon - ✅ Nov 9th 2019&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take the high speed train to Guangzhou - ✅ Dec 6th night&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Balayage my hair - ✅ Nov 21st 2019&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pass driving exam &amp;amp; get a HK driving license - Dec 23rd (Embasssingly failed the test)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go bouldering with friends&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get a whale shark tattoo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visit the Jumbo Floating restaurant - the scene of god of cookery&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Photoshoot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Iris Liu</name></author><summary type="html">I was leaving for Los Angelos on 24th December 2019. At the time, I created this bucket list to create memories with families and friends before leaving Home Kong 🇭🇰! Goodbye for now.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My first 50Km - A note to myself</title><link href="http://localhost:4444/blog/my-first-50Km" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My first 50Km - A note to myself" /><published>2019-10-26T03:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-10-26T03:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4444/blog/my-first-50Km</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4444/blog/my-first-50Km">&lt;p&gt;Dear Iris,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You used to think it’s impossible. You signed up for a full marathon because you wanted to travel to Osaka. You’ve never ran more than 15K at that point. And you did it. You thought that was it, that was the longest run you’ll have ever done and decided to hang up your shoes. Then you met a brunch of amazing friends who run with you. They are so inspiring and genuine that they made you fell in love with running again. This time you run on the trails, you’ve never felt so free and so connected when you run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few months ago you had the opportunity to participate in a 50km running race. It was your first ever ultra run, and was during a fairly stressful period when you were recovering from an ankle injury. So you hesitated. You started doubting yourself if you can really do it. Your mind started to make up excuses convincing yourself that it’s alright if you don’t do it. You could have rested and gone on a holiday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you couldn’t let go of it - the one challenge that you took on and you were determined to conquer it no matter what. You started training along with paying extra care to your injury and any signals that your body and mind gave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I admire your courage. You didn’t let fear took place. Fear of performing poorly, fear of getting injured, fear of exhausted body conditions, fear of disappointing the ones who supported me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am so glad you took on the challenge, finished the run with no injuries and more importantly you had a BLAST!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to document these powerful moments for you. The moment you saw your fear but you did not let it overpower you. Instead you set your heart and mind to conquer it and you did. Whenever you face challenges or setbacks in future, I hope you can keep this in mind - “Embrace your fear or failures and there is no boundaries to what you are doing.” xx&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With love from,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iris.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Iris Liu</name></author><category term="running" /><summary type="html">Dear Iris,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">HK50 2019 Race Report</title><link href="http://localhost:4444/blog/hk50-race-report" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="HK50 2019 Race Report" /><published>2019-10-26T03:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-10-26T03:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4444/blog/hk50-race-report</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4444/blog/hk50-race-report">&lt;p&gt;I checked off a 50Km ultra run in my bucket list before the end of 2019. The run was a dream, a sweet dream for me. And now I’m proud to call myself an ultra runner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/HK50/HK50_start_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Start&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The starting line of HK50 at The Peak&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/HK50/HK50_start_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Start&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;7am Beep!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I signed up for HK50 in May 2019, back then when I just started trail running. Yes, I decided to do a 50km race when I have gotten into trail running for 5 months. I met a friend, Lyndsey, who invited me to join her in a casual run in Aberdeen Country Park. I immediately fell in love at it, I felt so connected to the nature and got to see the beauty of Hong Kong that I have never looked at before (What a joke, I grew up and lived my entire life here in HK). Ever since, I met more amazing people of the running community and we did even more adventure runs together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the hindsight, running an ultra race had never crossed my mind. I had done a full marathon (41.95Km) in Osaka in November 2018. It was tough, my hips, my thighs, my calves were in pain. And why do I want to get myself to a run that is beyond the distance of a full marathon? Why do I have to put myself in so much pain and exhaustion? What do I get after I finish the run? I think it was the “Challenge” itself. I want to see myself getting better, doing things I used to think is impossible, pushing the limits and boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put in the training after I signed up and set myself up for the challenge. Things went well until I sprained my ankle after a big climb running back from the Sunset peak. It was a very hot day in August and I was exhausted, I didn’t have proper nutrition and I felt weak. Eventually, I stepped on a rock and twisted my left ankle. It was pretty bad. I got partial tear in my ankle’s ligaments and I had to stop from my training plan. After a month of (almost) no running and ankle strengthening, I return back to the trails, this time realizing the importance of strength and stability as well as proper nutrition and rest. I implemented these strategies to my weekly runs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;game-day&quot;&gt;Game day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The start of the course was at the Peak. My dad drove me to the start and I had my breakfast of overnight oat and banana in his car. I arrived at 6.15am. Weather is chill and not too sunny, perfect for a long run. I got myself warm ups and checked on my nutrition and gears. Everything is ready, and we start at 7am. The first half is the good flat HK trail section 1-4. I was familiar with the route since I did a couple of runs with friends in HK trails. Plus I did a 45K run with Amanda and friends two weeks before. The first half was pretty okay for me, I ran slightly faster than the average pace while thoroughly enjoying ‘the fly’. Second half was a route with lots of short steep climbs going around Mt Parker, then the fun starts with Mt Butler, Jardines Lookout and Violet Hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/HK50/HK50_route.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Route&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The fun 50km route with flatter 1st half in HK trail and short steep climbs in the 2nd climb&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was at a point of running 35K, I felt a bit of tiredness and stiffness in my legs. I made sure I took enough time and well fed at the final checkpoint, right before the climb of Mt Butler. It was tough, stairs after stairs. My strategy was running the flats and downstairs while walking the upstairs. It surely works. Slow and steady, yet I was passing people who stopped at the stairs. At the final 6K, I still got the energy and I wanted to catch up, so I pushed hard on climbing the violet hill. I passed quite some people at that point and we were cheering for one another. The last 3K of catch-water back to the Wong Nai Chung Gap was the hardest. It was so close, however, my body was tired, my legs and my feet ached and there seem to be a never ending path in the front. The last bit was a run-walking to the finish line.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Iris Liu</name></author><category term="running" /><category term="race report" /><summary type="html">I checked off a 50Km ultra run in my bucket list before the end of 2019. The run was a dream, a sweet dream for me. And now I’m proud to call myself an ultra runner.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">6 months updates on my 10-day Vipassana meditation experience</title><link href="http://localhost:4444/blog/vipassana-experience" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="6 months updates on my 10-day Vipassana meditation experience" /><published>2019-10-01T03:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-10-01T03:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4444/blog/vipassana-experience</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4444/blog/vipassana-experience">&lt;p&gt;I went to the Vipassana Meditation Center in Lantau, Hong Kong for a new student’s ten day course about 6 months ago in April 2019. I completed it and I
went home thinking “I’m fixed”. This is a journal of how and why it came about as well as my experiences during and after the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-1-the-why&quot;&gt;Part 1. The Why&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am always interested in human minds (my research interest is to teach machines how to think as humans.), how we think, perceive, feel and react. Of all the skills I could possibly obtain, I would like to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;master my mind&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Knowing how my brain is wired can potentially lead to clues to unwire it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Similar to programming, if we know the how the logic of the program is written, we can easily fix existing bugs in the program, prevent new bugs, and even rewrite the entire program. And that is very powerful - we will no longer feel all the negative thoughts that limit us and since our minds also control our physical bodies, we can reach our full potential, mentally and physically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not find Vipassana, Vipassana found me. Before I heard of Vipassana meditation, I barely even know and do meditation. It was the time when I experienced serious burnout in my work as a software engineer and decided to “resign naked” to search for my purposes and direction and then my colleague at the time mentioned Vipassana in our conversation. She didn’t even go to the 10-day Vipassana course herself, but she recommended me to give meditation a try and said that the course provides an excellent environment to learn the meditation techniques. Later, I confirmed by having a prep talk with another friend who recently completed the course. Well, I had no plan at the time and if it would help calm the mind and give me the headspace to think about my next moves, that was good enough for me to try it (plus it’s completely free).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-2-the-fix-day-1---10&quot;&gt;Part 2. The fix, Day 1 - 10&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived at the camp on the evening of the 10th. The day I arrived was an orientation day. All students observed “noble silence”: which means no communication, either by speaking or contact or gestures, with any other students. Noble silence started 7pm, and the course had officially started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The daily schedule was not easy for me. It included an early morning and night routine, along with 11 hours of meditation practice. It was as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4am - rise&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.30 - 6.30am - meditation (2 hours)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6.30 - 8am - breakfast&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8 - 11am - meditation (3 hours)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11 - 1pm - lunch&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 - 5pm - meditation (4 hours)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5 - 6pm - tea break (there is no dinner)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6 - 7pm - meditation (1 hour)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7 - 8pm - discourse (1 hour)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8 - 9pm - meditation (1 hour)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9.30pm - lights out&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put my 10-day vipassana experience in brief:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 1: &lt;em&gt;Felt uncomfortable, skeptical about the techniques. Thoughts were like untamed elephants, I could not focus.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 2: &lt;em&gt;Full of doubts, experienced physical and mental discomfort and pain. “Why I was stuck here?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 3: &lt;em&gt;Felt annoyed and grumpy. “Why I was getting no where? Fine, I’ll out patient everyone and complete the course (due to ego).”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 4: &lt;em&gt;Felt emotional and frustrated. “I am here to master my mind, WHAT”S THE POINT OF ALL THESE???” Doubts was cleared by teacher at night, practice went on.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 5: &lt;em&gt;First time feeling okay with the whole day sitting. I was working on something.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 6: &lt;em&gt;Woaw, I could observe my thoughts… they were noisy! I would keep trying to focus on my meditation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 7: &lt;em&gt;I couldn’t sleep because of someone nearby with a very loud snoring problem. Slept deprived for 6 days, I decided to wake the person up. Only when I found out that person was at the far end of the big dorm, I realized it was my mind which reacted to the snoring noise. If I noticed my mind was so untamed and could magnify the noise, that means I could also shut the noise down by controlling my mind. MIND WAS BLOWN.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 8: &lt;em&gt;I got it, it was all about THE MIND. I could observe most sensation on my body and my thoughts without reacting to them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 9: &lt;em&gt;Meditation made me feel good. Now everything made sense and appeared clearer. I felt relieved, free and genuinely happy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 10: &lt;em&gt;Noble silence ended. Excited to connect to other people and first time found out how talking could be tiring, mentally and physically. More thoughts were generated than the previous days and they made me harder to focus on meditation. Overall, I have experienced meditation as a powerful tool to master my mind and bring compassion to people around me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My vipassana experience was like a brain surgery, for me, there was so much pain and also so much joy. I’m glad I gave it a try and completed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-3-the-insight&quot;&gt;Part 3. The insight&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The takeaways of the vipassana journey can be summarized as below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Path of Dhamma&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Dhamma” is an interesting term in the vipassana journey. It means the universal law of nature. The path is divided into 3 sections, sila, samadi, and panna.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sila - the abstain from unwholesome deeds of body and speech.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is like the foundation principle. If we want to live in peace and harmony within ourselves and with others, we have to practice what we preach - have the right speech, perform the right action, and live the right livelihood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Samadhi - the wholsesome action of developing mastery over one’s mind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The habit pattern of our mind is to wander to the future or in the past, which can be a waste of energy. And often during those times, we generate negativity or craving. Through the practice of awareness, simply by observing the natural aspiration, we can train our mind to be aware at the present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Panna - the development of wisdom, of insight, which totally purifies the mind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practicing sila and samadhi is not enough, according to vipassana. The two techniques can help sharpen the mind, but neither of them is able to penetrate to the depths of the unconscious mind to eradicate all the impurities hidden and set us free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Pain is inevitable, suffering is optional.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Panna emphasizes experimental wisdom - the understanding of truth through personal experience, rather than received and intellectual wisdom. The truth is everything in the world is ever-changing, meaning they keep arising and passing away. Only when we experience the reality of impermanence within ourselves, we develop the real wisdom - and we won’t react to things that will eventually pass away (though it is easier said than done :p).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vipassana&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vipassana teaches the art of dying - how to die peacefully and harmoniously. And we learns the art of dying by learning the art of living - how to become the master of the present moment. There are two aspects of the technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Breaking the barrier between conscious &amp;amp; subconscious levels of mind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reactions occur at the unconscious level. By the time they reach the conscious level of mind, they become so intense and easily overpower the mind. With the practice of Vipassana, it trains our mind becomes conscious and aware the whole time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Equanimity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It teaches us how to maintain a balanced, harmonious mind. Given we aware of all the experiences and sensation, we should not to react to them, neither creating attachment or aversion towards those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the coolest part of all, by maintaining equanimity, we unwire the wiring and break the chain of old pattern of the mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-4-now-what&quot;&gt;Part 4. Now what?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the 10-day experience, I felt so refreshing and free. For a good moment, I thought this was it. I have gone through the experience and I was fixed. Change was about to happen and it will last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lucky enough, some changes did happen to me. Immediately after the meditation camp, I got to work with a professor on the field of neural networks and machine learning, which aligns with my areas of interests. I was also admitted to the Master’s program in computer science in University of Southern California to further my studies in one of the most exciting areas - data science and artificial intelligence. Although I did not contribute those things to joining the vipassana meditation course, I have gained the clarity and I confirmed them as something I would like to pursuit at this stage of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Am I fixed now?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, and I do not need to. Meditation is called a practice for a reason. It is a never-ending process. As long as you keep working on it consistently, like everything you do in life, you will see improvements and results. My result is gaining clarity in fulfilling my purposes and achieving things I want in life - family, personal growth, careers, health, fitness, finances, personal contribution etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;How do I find time to practice meditation daily?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the course, it is recommended to follow a 2-hour meditation practice daily (Let’s be honest, it is difficult and we don’t have time.).  I believe it all comes down to priority in life. I experience the benefits of vipassana - the clarity and peace, hence I aim doing 1 hour meditation daily, preferably in the early morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I miss a session, I will not be pissed by myself. I will continue in the next day (it’s all about the equanimity! You failed, and you keep trying the next time). Another tips is to join the short courses (1/ 3 days) and a long course from time to time to refresh the skills. Group sitting works for some people as well. Finding your community and organizing group meditation in your areas are great ways to keep the consistent practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;useful-resources&quot;&gt;Useful Resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Altered Traits: Science Reveals How Meditation Changes Your Mind, Brain, and Body by Daniel Goleman, Richard Davidson&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Siddhartha’s Brain: Unlocking the Ancient Science of Enlightenment
by James Kingsland&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The art of living by William Hart&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The discourse summaries by S.N. Goenka&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Iris Liu</name></author><category term="meditation" /><category term="mental health" /><summary type="html">I went to the Vipassana Meditation Center in Lantau, Hong Kong for a new student’s ten day course about 6 months ago in April 2019. I completed it and I went home thinking “I’m fixed”. This is a journal of how and why it came about as well as my experiences during and after the course.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I went from a software engineer to a research assistant? Industry vs academia?</title><link href="http://localhost:4444/blog/why-I-transit-from-SE-to-research" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I went from a software engineer to a research assistant? Industry vs academia?" /><published>2019-08-05T03:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-08-05T03:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4444/blog/why-I-transit-from-SE-to-research</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4444/blog/why-I-transit-from-SE-to-research">&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently transited from working as a software engineer in a technology startups to a research assistant (RA) in electrical engineering. People are often interested and even surprised in my transition from working in the tech industry to academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How are you going to adjust between the research work and latest technology in the industry? How do you find the pay between a software engineer and a research assistant?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have faced similar questions and doubts at the time I made the decision. In the hindsight, it made perfect sense for me to go back to school and pick up research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you’re in similar situation, deciding whether to go back to school from working in the industry. I’d suggest you to really ask yourself why and list down the reasons why you think you should whether go back to academia or stay in the industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are five reasons why I went back to the academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pursue-your-interests&quot;&gt;Pursue your interests&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is obvious and a very important one. Interest in conducting innovative research on a specific domain should be the number one why you choose working on research instead of working in the industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I have a passion in the fields of machine learning, deep learning, and computer vision. And at that time, I want to devote more time to manifest my interests in designing and implementing machine learning and deep learning and I believe working on research with my supervisor provide me with the opportunity to pursue my interests with full concentration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jumping back to the academia may seem to be a risky decision for some people, especially for those who have worked in the industry for a while. But you never know what you like / dislike unless you have tried.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, the opportunity cost for me to get back to research at this stage of my life is much lower than someone in their late twenties/ thirties to do so. Hence, if you have the time and cost, my advice is to follow your passion and go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;get-more-research-opportunities&quot;&gt;Get more research opportunities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A software engineer is a technical position in an organisation. The main job is to achieve the organisation’s goals with skills in coding, implementing algorithms, building system architecture etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whereas a research assistant (in EE / CS) is to continuously develop domain expertise in an area of interest and translate research into publications, codes and result with academic values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, I want to prepare myself for my master’s study as well as research-oriented jobs (such as research scientist, research engineer). Hence, I opt for taking some time to work in the research of my interest before starting my master’s study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;change-career-fields&quot;&gt;Change career fields&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To transit from one career field to another, getting into research can be a gateway to widen your career choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jump directly from one career field to another with neither previous working experience nor education background in a particular field can sometimes be hard. Imagine a software engineer in a medical technology company who want to transit into a director of Medical Informatics, there may be a gap to bridge. Especially the latter one may require knowledge in informatics and organisational management skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comparatively, it may be easier to obtain research opportunity in a multidisciplinary field, say biomedical informatics given your previous background is in computer science. With the research experience in a new field, one can obtain new domain expertises and skillsets that allow one to explore broader career choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;further-your-studies&quot;&gt;Further your studies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a research assistant can be a stepping stone for furthering study as a Master’s / PhD student. It is common for perspective Master’s / PhD student to work with their potential supervisor as a RA prior to their start of the study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one side, you can get to know the professor and the research center and increase the chance continuing working with the professor - be it PhD student or on-campus RA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other side, it can be an opportunity to see whether there is a good chemistry between you and your supervisor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;want-freedom--flexibility&quot;&gt;Want freedom &amp;amp; flexibility&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Academia is a great environment for researches whereas industry is driven mostly by revenue and results related to the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the bright sides of being a research assistant is that you can enjoy a higher level of control over your projects. As a research assistant, I have more time and resources devoted to projects in an area of interest to me, which is usually not the case in companies and organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have a higher flexibility in term of the style fo work. I have the freedom to decide my types of work, where to place, who to work with and when to work etc as a research staff in academic as long as I produce satisfactory result to my supervisor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, freedom and flexibility comes with responsibility and discipline. Otherwise, it can be adversely affect your research productivity and work ethnics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, this article has provided you with insights if you are considering into getting back to research as a software engineer. Thanks for reading! If you have any questions or suggestions, please leave a comment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--
The idea of starting a personal blog has been swirling around my head for some time, and I think the best way to shut it down is to create one.

### There are a few things that you should know up-front:
1. Ghost is designed for ambitious, professional publishers who want to actively build a business around their content. That's who it works best for. If you're using Ghost for some other purpose, that's fine too - but it might not be the best choice for you.
2. The entire platform can be modified and customized to suit your needs, which is very powerful, but doing so **does** require some knowledge of code. Ghost is not necessarily a good platform for beginners or people who just want a simple personal blog.
3. For the best experience we recommend downloading the Ghost Desktop App for your computer, which is the best way to access your Ghost site on a desktop device.


Ghost is made by an independent non-profit organisation called the Ghost Foundation. We are 100% self funded by revenue from our [Ghost(Pro)](https://ghost.org/pricing) service, and every penny we make is re-invested into funding further development of free, open source technology for modern journalism.

The main thing you'll want to read about next is probably: [the Ghost editor](https://demo.ghost.io/the-editor/).

Once you're done reading, you can simply delete the default **Ghost** user from your team to remove all of these introductory posts! --&gt;</content><author><name>Iris Liu</name></author><category term="tech" /><category term="research" /><summary type="html">I’ve recently transited from working as a software engineer in a technology startups to a research assistant (RA) in electrical engineering. People are often interested and even surprised in my transition from working in the tech industry to academia.</summary></entry></feed>