<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="http://localhost:4444/blog/tag/meditation/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="http://localhost:4444/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-09-28T00:39:08-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://localhost:4444/blog/tag/meditation/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">Iris Liu | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>A blog of a computer scientist and ultra runner</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">6 months updates on my 10-day Vipassana meditation experience</title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4444/blog/vipassana-experience" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="6 months updates on my 10-day Vipassana meditation experience" />
      <published>2019-10-01T03:00:00-07:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-01T03:00:00-07:00</updated>
      <id>http://localhost:4444/blog/vipassana-experience</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4444/blog/vipassana-experience">&lt;p&gt;I went to the Vipassana Meditation Center in Lantau, Hong Kong for a new student’s ten day course about 6 months ago in April 2019. I completed it and I
went home thinking “I’m fixed”. This is a journal of how and why it came about as well as my experiences during and after the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-1-the-why&quot;&gt;Part 1. The Why&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am always interested in human minds (my research interest is to teach machines how to think as humans.), how we think, perceive, feel and react. Of all the skills I could possibly obtain, I would like to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;master my mind&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Knowing how my brain is wired can potentially lead to clues to unwire it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Similar to programming, if we know the how the logic of the program is written, we can easily fix existing bugs in the program, prevent new bugs, and even rewrite the entire program. And that is very powerful - we will no longer feel all the negative thoughts that limit us and since our minds also control our physical bodies, we can reach our full potential, mentally and physically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not find Vipassana, Vipassana found me. Before I heard of Vipassana meditation, I barely even know and do meditation. It was the time when I experienced serious burnout in my work as a software engineer and decided to “resign naked” to search for my purposes and direction and then my colleague at the time mentioned Vipassana in our conversation. She didn’t even go to the 10-day Vipassana course herself, but she recommended me to give meditation a try and said that the course provides an excellent environment to learn the meditation techniques. Later, I confirmed by having a prep talk with another friend who recently completed the course. Well, I had no plan at the time and if it would help calm the mind and give me the headspace to think about my next moves, that was good enough for me to try it (plus it’s completely free).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-2-the-fix-day-1---10&quot;&gt;Part 2. The fix, Day 1 - 10&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived at the camp on the evening of the 10th. The day I arrived was an orientation day. All students observed “noble silence”: which means no communication, either by speaking or contact or gestures, with any other students. Noble silence started 7pm, and the course had officially started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The daily schedule was not easy for me. It included an early morning and night routine, along with 11 hours of meditation practice. It was as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4am - rise&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.30 - 6.30am - meditation (2 hours)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6.30 - 8am - breakfast&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8 - 11am - meditation (3 hours)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11 - 1pm - lunch&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 - 5pm - meditation (4 hours)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5 - 6pm - tea break (there is no dinner)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6 - 7pm - meditation (1 hour)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7 - 8pm - discourse (1 hour)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8 - 9pm - meditation (1 hour)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9.30pm - lights out&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put my 10-day vipassana experience in brief:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 1: &lt;em&gt;Felt uncomfortable, skeptical about the techniques. Thoughts were like untamed elephants, I could not focus.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 2: &lt;em&gt;Full of doubts, experienced physical and mental discomfort and pain. “Why I was stuck here?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 3: &lt;em&gt;Felt annoyed and grumpy. “Why I was getting no where? Fine, I’ll out patient everyone and complete the course (due to ego).”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 4: &lt;em&gt;Felt emotional and frustrated. “I am here to master my mind, WHAT”S THE POINT OF ALL THESE???” Doubts was cleared by teacher at night, practice went on.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 5: &lt;em&gt;First time feeling okay with the whole day sitting. I was working on something.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 6: &lt;em&gt;Woaw, I could observe my thoughts… they were noisy! I would keep trying to focus on my meditation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 7: &lt;em&gt;I couldn’t sleep because of someone nearby with a very loud snoring problem. Slept deprived for 6 days, I decided to wake the person up. Only when I found out that person was at the far end of the big dorm, I realized it was my mind which reacted to the snoring noise. If I noticed my mind was so untamed and could magnify the noise, that means I could also shut the noise down by controlling my mind. MIND WAS BLOWN.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 8: &lt;em&gt;I got it, it was all about THE MIND. I could observe most sensation on my body and my thoughts without reacting to them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 9: &lt;em&gt;Meditation made me feel good. Now everything made sense and appeared clearer. I felt relieved, free and genuinely happy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 10: &lt;em&gt;Noble silence ended. Excited to connect to other people and first time found out how talking could be tiring, mentally and physically. More thoughts were generated than the previous days and they made me harder to focus on meditation. Overall, I have experienced meditation as a powerful tool to master my mind and bring compassion to people around me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My vipassana experience was like a brain surgery, for me, there was so much pain and also so much joy. I’m glad I gave it a try and completed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-3-the-insight&quot;&gt;Part 3. The insight&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The takeaways of the vipassana journey can be summarized as below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Path of Dhamma&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Dhamma” is an interesting term in the vipassana journey. It means the universal law of nature. The path is divided into 3 sections, sila, samadi, and panna.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sila - the abstain from unwholesome deeds of body and speech.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is like the foundation principle. If we want to live in peace and harmony within ourselves and with others, we have to practice what we preach - have the right speech, perform the right action, and live the right livelihood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Samadhi - the wholsesome action of developing mastery over one’s mind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The habit pattern of our mind is to wander to the future or in the past, which can be a waste of energy. And often during those times, we generate negativity or craving. Through the practice of awareness, simply by observing the natural aspiration, we can train our mind to be aware at the present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Panna - the development of wisdom, of insight, which totally purifies the mind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practicing sila and samadhi is not enough, according to vipassana. The two techniques can help sharpen the mind, but neither of them is able to penetrate to the depths of the unconscious mind to eradicate all the impurities hidden and set us free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Pain is inevitable, suffering is optional.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Panna emphasizes experimental wisdom - the understanding of truth through personal experience, rather than received and intellectual wisdom. The truth is everything in the world is ever-changing, meaning they keep arising and passing away. Only when we experience the reality of impermanence within ourselves, we develop the real wisdom - and we won’t react to things that will eventually pass away (though it is easier said than done :p).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vipassana&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vipassana teaches the art of dying - how to die peacefully and harmoniously. And we learns the art of dying by learning the art of living - how to become the master of the present moment. There are two aspects of the technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Breaking the barrier between conscious &amp;amp; subconscious levels of mind.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reactions occur at the unconscious level. By the time they reach the conscious level of mind, they become so intense and easily overpower the mind. With the practice of Vipassana, it trains our mind becomes conscious and aware the whole time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Equanimity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It teaches us how to maintain a balanced, harmonious mind. Given we aware of all the experiences and sensation, we should not to react to them, neither creating attachment or aversion towards those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the coolest part of all, by maintaining equanimity, we unwire the wiring and break the chain of old pattern of the mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;part-4-now-what&quot;&gt;Part 4. Now what?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the 10-day experience, I felt so refreshing and free. For a good moment, I thought this was it. I have gone through the experience and I was fixed. Change was about to happen and it will last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lucky enough, some changes did happen to me. Immediately after the meditation camp, I got to work with a professor on the field of neural networks and machine learning, which aligns with my areas of interests. I was also admitted to the Master’s program in computer science in University of Southern California to further my studies in one of the most exciting areas - data science and artificial intelligence. Although I did not contribute those things to joining the vipassana meditation course, I have gained the clarity and I confirmed them as something I would like to pursuit at this stage of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Am I fixed now?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, and I do not need to. Meditation is called a practice for a reason. It is a never-ending process. As long as you keep working on it consistently, like everything you do in life, you will see improvements and results. My result is gaining clarity in fulfilling my purposes and achieving things I want in life - family, personal growth, careers, health, fitness, finances, personal contribution etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;How do I find time to practice meditation daily?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the course, it is recommended to follow a 2-hour meditation practice daily (Let’s be honest, it is difficult and we don’t have time.).  I believe it all comes down to priority in life. I experience the benefits of vipassana - the clarity and peace, hence I aim doing 1 hour meditation daily, preferably in the early morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I miss a session, I will not be pissed by myself. I will continue in the next day (it’s all about the equanimity! You failed, and you keep trying the next time). Another tips is to join the short courses (1/ 3 days) and a long course from time to time to refresh the skills. Group sitting works for some people as well. Finding your community and organizing group meditation in your areas are great ways to keep the consistent practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;useful-resources&quot;&gt;Useful Resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Altered Traits: Science Reveals How Meditation Changes Your Mind, Brain, and Body by Daniel Goleman, Richard Davidson&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Siddhartha’s Brain: Unlocking the Ancient Science of Enlightenment
by James Kingsland&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The art of living by William Hart&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The discourse summaries by S.N. Goenka&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Iris Liu</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="meditation" />
      
        <category term="mental health" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I went to the Vipassana Meditation Center in Lantau, Hong Kong for a new student’s ten day course about 6 months ago in April 2019. I completed it and I went home thinking “I’m fixed”. This is a journal of how and why it came about as well as my experiences during and after the course.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
