<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="http://localhost:4444/blog/tag/bjj/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="http://localhost:4444/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-01-02T18:53:25-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://localhost:4444/blog/tag/bjj/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">Iris Liu | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>A blog of a computer scientist and ultra runner</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">I won a silver in Grand Canyon Jit Jitsu Tournament</title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4444/blog/I-won-a-silver-grandcanyon-bjj" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I won a silver in Grand Canyon Jit Jitsu Tournament" />
      <published>2020-12-14T02:00:00-08:00</published>
      <updated>2020-12-14T02:00:00-08:00</updated>
      <id>http://localhost:4444/blog/I-won-a-silver-grandcanyon-bjj</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4444/blog/I-won-a-silver-grandcanyon-bjj">&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday I completed in my first Brazillian Jit Jitsu Tournament in Grand Canyon State and won a silver home! My first tounament as a white belt. Fresh white belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 months ago I start learning Brazillian Jit Jitsu under Clube De Jit Jitsu. I immediately fell in love with this martial art. One of the things I love is everyone in the gym is very enthusiatic about jit jitsu. Their passion in jit jitsu incfluenced me to want more, more into the sports. I remembered one day after class, I told my professor “I want to compete!”. He looked surprised and “Sure! Iris, you know… You need to show aggression in the competition.” This has sticked to my mind. It’s not a game, it is a fight! I need to get my body and mind in shape. Ever since, I paid full attention in every class, drilled the techniques, applied it to my rolling partners, recorded and learnt from the mistakes and repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tournament was in Arizona. It was a 6 and a half hours drive from Los Angeles. Competing across the states in the midst seemed uneccessary. I had thought about giving up but thought I could have done it safely and cautiously. I started one-on-one training with my training partner every morning in the gym before my school commitment. This past month’s nonstop practuses was the best part of it. I drilled the skills until it built in my muscle memory. I learnt not just the moves or maneuvers, but also why I did it and how I could counter the move when I got caught up in it. I understood my strengths and weaknesses, my body and how I could leverage them to develop my A game for the competition. More importantly, the more I rolled, the more confidence I had built. Rolling with my jit jitsu sisters was one of the happiest moments. We learnt from one another and selflessly share the skills and empower one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/bjjGrandCanyon2020/bjj_first_match.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Start&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I signed and pulled my biggest smile after I won the first match&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t care other girls in the bracket were trained many months or they were taller or heavier than me. I knew I was ready. I gave it all. The first match was tough and I won. The second one didn’t go so well and I learnt a lot. But wan’t that the fun part of competitions? I won a silver. It was like a sweet dream. I was exhausted but I gave my biggest smile when the referee raised my arm up. I couldn’t be more proud of myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am so grateful and thankful for everyone who supported me and made this event possible! Still a white belt but that means I have only one direction to grow ⬆️.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Iris Liu</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="tournament" />
      
        <category term="bjj" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Last Saturday I completed in my first Brazillian Jit Jitsu Tournament in Grand Canyon State and won a silver home! My first tounament as a white belt. Fresh white belt.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
